Hi, I'm Wendy Finerman,
one of the producers of Forrest Gump,
and it gives me great pleasure
that with this DVD
we will be able to bring Forrest
into many more homes across the world.
I think what's so rewarding here
is that Forrest is a little bit of everyone,
and when I first read the novel
Forrest Gump, by Winston Groom,
I imagined what the world would be like
if everybody had come in contact
with a man like Forrest.
He was so honest. He was so simple.
He had a way of looking at people,
incidents, history, animals, nature
in ways that I don't think anybody
had ever quite seen the world before.
And with a lot of effort,
on hundreds and hundreds
and hundreds of people's parts,
I think that the movie that was made
took that story to a level that was higher
than any of us had ever imagined.
Eric Roth wrote the blueprint
for the movie
that everybody else... So graciously
and diligently and in a dignified way
just kind of made it, just, to a level
that none of us
could have ever imagined.
The icing on the cake
for this amazing screenplay
was to have Tom Hanks
as Forrest Gump.
Even though Forrest appears as such
a simpleton, he's truly very complex.
There is no one else
who could have played this role.
The image of Forrest
sitting on the bus bench
is exactly how the screenplay starts,
and the feather is the touch
that Eric brought us into,
and I think his intention was destiny.
I think when Bob let that feather float
in the beginning of the movie
and ended up right at Forrest's toe,
it set the tone for the wonderful journey
that was ahead of us.
Tom came to play this part
because Eric and Tom and I
had been actually working
on another project together,
and we had talked to Tom
about doing it,
and he, kind of,
was somewhat interested,
and once Eric came aboard, yeah,
he was somewhat interested,
and once Eric wrote the screenplay,
Tom was there.
You know, there was no question
about what the screenplay did,
in terms of moving all of us.
And there was really only one man
that we thought
could give the screenplay its life,
and that was Bob Zemeckis.
Because we had no idea
who else there would be
that could mix both the magic,
the imagery,
and be able to take us places visually
that we'd never gone before.
And obviously Bob went so far beyond
our wildest imaginations in doing that.
One of the things that I remember,
in the beginning,
sitting down and talking to Bob about,
was his vision of the movie.
And one of the things, the images
that he talked about in particular
with the scene with the doctor's office,
was Norman Rockwell.
And he talked about Americana,
and he even talked about
that industrial avocado-green.
And he always
wanted to present a picture
that could be accessible to anybody,
and so anybody could kind of
put themselves in that place,
so therefore, they would have
an easier way of understanding
who Forrest was in that place.
And just like this doctor that we see,
and we've all seen
those kind of medicine cabinets,
and we've all seen that kind of room,
made us very comfortable in meeting
this very, very unusual character.
I think what gave Forrest the strength,
from his inception, was his mother.
'Cause his mother always said,
"You know what, Forrest? You're not
more different than anyone else,"
I think were her exact words.
And she allowed him
to have the confidence
that I think all of us as parents today
wish that we are able
to give our own children.
Bob's vision of mixing mediums,
in terms of stock footage
and special effects
and other things like that,
were also able to take us
where Forrest's imagination took us.
Bob knew exactly what he wanted to do
when he put Forrest
in the kind of braces that he put on him.
From the beginning of imagining
what he would be like,
I truly believe, in his mind,
he knew what it was gonna be like
when Forrest would break free
and run from those braces.
And every little moment,
which is amazing
about working with Bob is,
I really think he sees
what he's going to do today,
and knows where it's gonna come out
in the future.
Oak Alley is a wonderful place,
that we kind of all fell in love
with the South.
I remember when we were driving
around looking for different places,
it was very important
that the trees kind of made you feel,
with that Spanish moss,
of right away
you know you're in the South,
right away you know
you're in a place of heritage,
you're in a place of home.
And one of the things
that was most important to everyone,
and in particular to Forrest,
was his home of Alabama.
Throughout every incident
that he went in his life,
if you notice, he always came home.
Home was where he was safe,
and, kind of, home was where
he knew he was comfortable.
The other thing that Bob did,
which was very interesting,
was in terms of Mama, in Sally,
was she was always a lady.
No matter what she did or what situation
you put her in, she was still a lady.
You never felt that he came
from an unfortunate house,
or he came from a place
where he was denied anything.
You felt like he came from
a very old, wonderful Southern house.
And it wasn't that they were rich
or they were poor,
but they were just what everybody
imagines the South to be.
So right away, everybody kind of
understood where Forrest came from.
I think every parent has a fear
of when you sit there and you look...
And somebody sits there
and calls you in and says,
"How is your child doing in school?"
And what Mama had to deal with
was what every parent's
fear and nightmare is
that they'd have to deal with.
And the way that she kind of said,
"My son's not gonna be any different.
I don't care what you say,"
led the road for Forrest ahead of him.
Bob had a wonderful way of knowing
what was gonna be funny
and just, kind of, could hear
the audiences roar with laughter,
even while he was filming a scene.
And, you know, it was amazing to have
somebody around who just knew...
I've never in my life, nor ever will
in my life, work with somebody
who has that ability
to put his finger right on
what will make people laugh
and make them cry.
Curious George is a really funny,
important thing to me,
'cause one day Eric was writing
the scene of Mama reading to Forrest,
and he said, "God, Wendy, I don't know.
What book should that be?"
And I remember running upstairs
to my daughter's bookcase
and I came across, in fact,
my old copy of Curious George,
and I ran back to Eric, and I said to him,
"Curious George, Curious George."
And we said,
"God, yeah, that makes sense."
And I always chuckle, personally,
at that notion of, there Forrest is
getting Curious George read to him
in the way that I read to my kids,
and by the way,
the way that everybody, I think,
across the world reads to their kids.
The boarding house
was a labour of love.
Rick Carter took it so seriously,
as he does with all of his work,
to make it authentic and real
and not movie over-the-top,
the way that you see in some movies.
That you see people
live well beyond their means
of who their characters would be.
Everything that was created
in this house
was to make it look like
it was authentic and real.
If you notice,
there's nothing overly lavish.
These are people who have
a nice, old Southern home,
but obviously anything
that was truly valuable
from the future
has been long gone or long sold.
Once Elvis came into the picture,
and Forrest learnt how to dance
and put two and two together,
I think the audience is well-aware
that they were on the road
to somewhere very, very special.
Michael Conner was an amazing find
of Ellen Lewis',
the young Forrest Gump.
We looked forever
and forever and forever.
We had searches
throughout the country.
We must have gone through
10,000 different faces,
and once we met him,
we knew he was it.
He had never been on a plane
when he flew out here
for the screen test.
He'd never really acted.
He only had directed
his own home movies.
And he had
a sense of innocence about him
that you know
that Forrest of youth would have had.
This is another special moment
for me, too.
The bus driver
bears my daughter's name,
and it was great how we meet her
in the 1950s,
and as all of you know,
we will see her again later.
And Bob has those little touches
of just making everybody kind of feel
comfortable in a very small-town way.
He also has a way
of picking out moments
that we all feel that we've been through.
I think everybody as a child
knows that one moment.
Where do you sit?
"Are people looking at me?
Am I the geek? Am I the nerd?"
And he has a way of capturing it,
in a way,
that you both have empathy
for the character,
and you also could have imagined,
"Oh, my God,
those were moments in my life,"
or, "They actually really were
moments in my life."
I remember this bus scene, 'cause we
were filming down there in the South,
and it was in August
and it was as hot as hot could be,
with more mosquitoes per square inch
than there ever lived.
And these little kids spent two days
driving back and forth
on this dirt road in the bus,
and the way they looked
is nothing compared to the way they felt.
One of the keys
to the beauty of Forrest Gump
is Forrest's love for Jenny.
From that moment, where that little girl
offered him a seat next to her,
a love affair of life took off.
They had a way of talking
with each other
and they had a truth
and they had an honesty.
And I think one of the main points
of the movie is unrequited love.
And I think that, from the second
that Forrest laid eyes on Jenny,
the whole movie took a turn
of his love story with Jenny.
Jenny, like Mama,
never looked at Forrest any differently,
and I don't know if that's the real reason
that he loved her,
or the reason that, in some ways,
she was a lost soul like he was.
One of the keys to finding Jenny
was who, as with Tom,
could number one, age 20 years,
basically go from high school
through mid-adult.
That was number one, really important,
because both of those characters had
to be able to play 16 all the way to 36.
One of the other things
was the chemistry
between the two of them,
because it is such a love story,
that what Bob insisted on,
and I think he was so brilliant about it,
was that we screen-test
whoever these two people would be,
so you really could tell
if there was magic between them.
And it's probably been one
of my greatest lessons in filmmaking,
and something that I truly now
do try to insist on,
if I ever can have it be possible is,
if somebody really, really wants
to play a part, they will screen-test for it.
And in fact, as you know,
and you'll see in the DVD,
that this is what Robin Wright did.
I also think that Robin kind of
had the look so much of a Jenny.
You knew
that she carried stories within her
that weren't quite always easy to tell
that she wore.
One of the fun parts for me, personally,
with Forrest, is that I'm a runner.
So, I could understand often
when he was going somewhere,
and how he was going, how he felt.
Not that I run like this,
or the wind, as Forrest would say,
but there's a great freedom
in, kind of, being out there and running,
and there's, kind of,
a great piece of mind.
And you kind of felt like wherever
he was running, he would feel that.
He would just run through anything
and it would, kind of, not even faze him.
It's also funny for us to look at today,
'cause children today have no idea
that you run or ride a bicycle
to somebody's house.
It's unheard of that...
In the South,
you would walk to somebody's house
and nobody would be scared.
You'd probably still do it today,
but in a lot of the big cities
that we all live in,
kids don't run around
and don't have the freedom that they do.
This scene of Jenny
being chased by her father
kind of led us all
to understand Jenny's pain,
and one of the reasons
why she probably fled a lot
throughout the rest of the movie.
Bob had an amazing way
of telling the story of her abuse
without getting graphic.
And, kind of, the birds were what
made us think of Jenny from then on,
and I remember
when Bob created those birds,
or rather Ken Ralston did,
digitally, for Bob.
They, kind of,
were a foreshadowing of Jenny's story.
Birds always go away,
but they always come home.
Just in the same way
that Forrest would run to Jenny's,
it was always wonderful for me,
with this scene,
that Jenny would come
to Forrest's house.
This scene's wonderful,
when they're lying in bed together,
'cause he gives her that little look
that you know
that he's, kind of,
growing up to be a man.
What was great in this transition
was we just went
from young Jenny and young Forrest
to older Jenny and older Forrest,
and we did it with such ease
that you never even noticed
that these two characters
had aged 10 years.
One of the other things that Forrest...
We all chuckled at,
and it actually was established
in the book,
was his sense of being
at a certain place, at a certain time
where something miraculous happened.
And when he gets discovered
by 'Bear' Bryant in this scene,
it is just, kind of, the chuckle
that leads us on his journey
of a lot of historic events
and a lot of famous people.
And what also was so great
is how the running was tied into
a lot of the things that Forrest does,
and it kind of gave him a special talent
that carried him through Alabama,
through Vietnam,
through, you know,
a cross-country marathon.
From a physical standpoint,
it was amazing what Bob did with this,
because this is... You have seen...
We're filming in a local stadium,
and all of those people, basically,
were computer-generated.
They were moved around and multiplied,
and you got the feeling
that you were in the Orange Bowl,
or wherever the classic would've been.
The amazing part about Forrest
in the Wallace scene
was we all knew he was not feeling
what the Southerners there
were feeling.
We know that he had no judgement
about going to school
with African-Americans.
We know he really didn't care.
He just was darn curious
of what all the commotion was about.
And by him being there,
he was able to touch
a little bit of history,
because when she dropped that book,
there was no other Southern student
who was gonna go up and pick it up
other than Forrest Gump.
One of the things that was so hard
in getting Forrest Gump made,
for the nine years
that it was in development,
was everybody thought
it was very episodic,
that it was not a story
with a traditional three-act structure.
And you kind of went from one episode
to another episode to another episode,
and what tied you all together
was this unbelievable character.
But yet, it was not presented
in the traditional way
that most movie stories are,
and ultimately, that was the thing
that people really, kind of,
grasped onto and loved,
is because they, kind of,
were just waiting every time to see
where Forrest would go
and where the story would take you.
And they never had any idea
of what was ahead or what was in store.
Forrest, in a lot of ways,
always came to Jenny's rescue.
And unfortunately,
often for his own benefit,
he didn't know what he was doing
or what situation he was in.
And she often was his reason.
She would try to make him
understand situations
of which he really wasn't capable.
Even with how mad she is at him
in this scene for ruining her date,
you know she can't help herself
but really loving this man.
One of the other
really, really wonderful things
that came to life when the movie
was made was the music.
Joel Sill chose so many songs,
that the moment that you would hear
a couple notes in the tune,
you'd know exactly where you are,
and it would set you in a time
and set you in a place.
And he did it in a way
that was very natural and not directed.
Bob also had a way,
at the end of any scene,
of cutting to something that would put,
like, a real little touch on it
that you didn't quite expect.
Just like the football players
falling on each other.
When Forrest and the president
shook hands for the first time,
it was an amazing moment for people.
I remember seeing audiences just gasp.
I remember seeing friends
see a clip of it,
just couldn't believe it would happen.
And it was something that, I think,
none of us
really quite realised the effect on,
'cause we had all been witness
to the preparation of it so much.
But it was truly one of the most
memorable moments in cinema,
because we really took
one of our most famous American icons
and had him meet Forrest Gump.
Some of the points of history
that we were taken through,
unfortunately, they would have
humorous moments with Forrest,
and then often
there would be a very sad button.
Whether it be George Wallace,
the Kennedys,
and other future moments.
But we kind of realised that that was
the period of time through the '60s,
that we made great strides
but there was also great sadness.
What's neat about
the bus scene to Vietnam is,
obviously, it mirrors the bus scene
when Forrest first went off to school,
and you kind of know,
from his friendship with Jenny,
that the moment he sits down
next to Bubba,
that will be his best friend,
just as Jenny is his best girl.
In the way that you knew that Jenny
had her past and her damages,
that she was in some ways
a damaged soul,
it was kind of similar to the way
that Bubba looked at the world
in a little bit different way
than most people,
and kind of in the same way
that Forrest looked at it.
Just a little bit cockeyed.
I think, for all of us, after all
of the shrimp through filming this movie,
and by the way, also being down
in Beaufort, South Carolina, living there,
which is a shrimping area itself,
I think that all of us
have had our shrimp,
probably for the rest of our life.
Once again, what made Forrest
so extraordinary in the military
was because
he just, kind of, did what he was told.
He didn't get distracted
in the way that often people,
let's put it this way, a higher intelligence
or larger capacity for life would have,
and I think that's what made him
such an extraordinary soldier.
Any of those simple tasks
that Forrest had,
he was just extraordinary at,
and I think that that was,
kind of, also the fun of showing him
to everybody in the world,
'cause I think everybody hopefully thinks
that there's one little thing
that they're extraordinary at,
and if you can find that one thing
you're extraordinary at,
you kind of know
what makes you feel good
and kind of understand where
everybody was rooting for Forrest.
There were moments in this movie
that none of us could foreshadow
what audiences would think,
and to hear everybody just roar
when Bubba cited
his thousands of shrimp recipes
was one of surprise and, I guess, glee.
The other thing is,
whenever there was a quiet moment,
you always knew
that Forrest was thinking of Jenny.
And I think, in some ways,
it comforted everyone to know
that he was not so lonely and sad,
but yet, he was always thinking of her.
And it was always important
that wherever you are in the movie,
you kind of had a feeling
of where Jenny was.
And the decision was conscious
to always not let too much time go by
without us realising where Jenny was,
what she was doing.
And also, at times, she supplied for us,
kind of, a benchmark in history
of what was happening
and what was changing.
At this point in the movie,
we're seeing Jenny and Forrest
go in two separate directions.
She, obviously, is becoming
a lot more anti-Vietnam.
He's on his way to Vietnam.
We both know that the future for them
together does not look great,
but once again, there he is, he sees her,
he's gonna notice her in distress,
and like her Prince Charming,
he comes to save her.
He always seemed to show up
at the perfect moment,
save her, and then yet, once again,
she'd always forgive him and, kind of,
be thankful that he was there.
But this time, when she knew
he was leaving, she was scared,
'cause I think everybody knew
what it meant
when you're going to Vietnam.
Robin Wright, in her portrayal,
she really often...
It's just seeing her and looking at her,
and you understand the time and place
of where she is and what she's doing.
And one of the things that great efforts
went into were her hairstyles,
if you look at them.
You know, she had numerous wigs.
Her hair went from long to short,
from a hippie to trying to be
a good Southern mother.
And little things
like touches of hairstyles,
it's amazing the effect they can have.
When we all sat down
and started talking about
who would be the perfect Mama,
it was funny,
Tom and I both came to,
kind of, the same conclusion,
that there was nobody better than Sally,
and we just saw that she was
what Mama Gump would be,
and she kind of is
what Mama Gump would be.
Lieutenant Dan's character
was just so out there.
We had a real difficulty thinking about
who would be
the perfect Lieutenant Dan,
and when Gary Sinise
walked into the room at Bob's office
and read the lines,
I remember everybody
just turned to themselves and said,
"Oh, my God, he's here."
And what was wonderful
about Gary was...
Gary is such a well-trained actor,
and he had never...
None of us would ever think of him
as being particularly funny,
and there were just comments
that came out of him,
like, the first time
we set our eyes on him in this scene,
that were absolutely hysterical.
It's amazing to look at the whole place
and know that
this was, again, a wetland side
of a marshy side of South Carolina
that probably was only about 40 minutes
from Mama's house.
And so much was done,
in terms of visual effects,
that will never be known to the viewer.
Mountains that were put in backgrounds.
The boys all went
into real military training
with Lieutenant Dale Dye,
who is a military expert,
and Parris Island
is a very famous marine base,
which was in the same locale
as where we were
shooting this movie, so...
We went one day and hung out
at a Marine shooting base
where everybody
truly did shoot real M16s
and stood and worked out
with real marines,
and everything, kind of, was done
so the actors could get a taste of reality,
so when they went to go portray it,
they really were in the mindset
of what was authentic.
When we cast all of these boys,
I think it was really important
that they were a little bit of everymen,
because I think that that's what,
for the most part,
our troops in Vietnam were made up of.
A cross-section
of the typical American boys
from all over the country.
Just as you're having a yearning
for what's going on back home,
the story comes and gives you
kind of what you would like.
And I think that's where a lot of people
found great peace in Forrest Gump,
because everything
that you were expecting back home
was not what you'd expect,
but still, it was answering questions
of what you were wondering.
One of the few things
that was taken from the book
was Forrest's friendship with Bubba.
Bubba, in the book, very much
like in the movie, in the script,
was truly Forrest's best friend.
He was the only person
who knew and understood Forrest,
and Forrest was the only person
who could probably know
and understand Bubba.
And what was also so important,
I think, to the story was,
what Bubba gave Forrest
was shrimping.
And probably one of the things
that Jenny helped encourage
with Forrest was running,
so both of these two key characters
in his life
were able to supply him with, probably,
two of the most necessary things
he had for surviving
in all the different situations that he did.
What was great with Jenny
was she let us have a little notion
of everything that was happening
during the '60s and the early '70s.
With just one little look at her,
one little glimpse,
you know exactly where she was going,
what she was doing,
what challenge she had,
and you could place her
in the time and the moment.
The filming of this sequence
was terrifying.
First of all, because it was so real.
You had the feeling of...
It was a combination
of days and days and days work,
but every little episode
that was constructed
and then to lay on each other was real.
It was intense,
and I remember watching Tom
carry all these bodies back and forth
and back and forth and back and forth,
and you knew they were actors,
and you knew it was makeup,
but somehow you knew
what it all meant.
No matter how crazy and intense
Lieutenant Dan was,
you really did know
he cared about his boys,
and you really did feel that he had
a true sense of responsibility for them,
and he understood
that both Forrest and Bubba
were probably a little more limited
in intelligence than some of his men.
For someone who people thought
had such a limited sense of intelligence,
Forrest was terribly devoted
and terribly responsible.
And I think everybody's heart sank
when he knew
that Bubba wasn't with him,
and he knew that Bubba
was probably in trouble.
The moment that Forrest finds Bubba
is probably
the largest moment of growth
that he's had in his life
up until this very moment.
And I think this is truly the moment
that he's become a man,
when I think he's witnessed loss
right before him.
And for me,
from the moment you read the script
to the moment
that Bubba is in his arms,
the word "home" is the kind of thing
that resonates with me to this day.
Just, "I want to go home."
It's also the first time
that we see Forrest's real pain
and his real loss.
When you come back to him this time,
and I think he's a different man than
he's ever been on the bench before.
Just as reality would really sink in,
Forrest Gump
would always do something
that was so absurd or being so crazy
that got you back
into the notion of the fun of the movie.
I think for everybody
who was on the set that day,
when Lieutenant Dan
was picked up without any legs,
even though we could see them
with the blue screen that was there,
was truly gasping,
because it was the first time,
as in many scenes in this movie,
that somebody had truly lost their legs.
And once again, just as he
was getting on the road to happiness,
he unfortunately
had to suffer a disappointment.
Ping-Pong is one of the fun things
that was also there in the book
that we altered slightly.
What's also fun is,
Forrest became good at things
that were just everyday things
to most people.
Nobody would ever think of being
a professional Ping-Pong player,
or where that would lead you,
which we all know where it led him to.
But, "Just keep the ball and watch,"
and there he went.
This stuff was really fun, because all
of the special effects stuff that we did...
Still, Tom had to become
a fairly good Ping-Pong player
to make it look
that it could be believable
that a ball would bounce like that.
Destiny is a very important part
of the whole movie.
Every character in the movie
has his or her destiny,
and Lieutenant Dan is the voice
for all of us as the audience,
because he's the only one who really
does acknowledge what destiny is
and what destiny's significance
is in everybody's journey.
I think it was a very conscious moment
of Eric Roth's
to include that destiny in there.
What was great was that Forrest
went back to the White House again,
and so many times in his life
he did things again.
Washington was a wonderful place
to shoot. It was amazing.
Wherever you were, you looked around
and just couldn't believe that you were
in front of the Washington Memorial,
the Lincoln Memorial, the White House.
It was truly, probably, one of the most
fun that we had for those 10 days.
We shot in front
of the Washington Memorial.
It was one of the coldest days
in November
that they had ever had in Washington.
And, in fact, we were on the news,
because we were recreating a day
that was quite warm,
and people were dressed very casually,
and with limited layers.
And it truly was, I think, in the 20s,
and we had people in flimsy
peasant dresses and sandals.
And every time we'd yell, "Cut,"
they'd be going to a hot soup line.
I think the other part that's really fun
is people like Abbie Hoffman.
A lot of people's children
would have no idea who he was,
and I think that Forrest was able
to educate people with important,
as I've said before, icons of history,
that you look at Abbie Hoffman
and exactly know
what the sentiment was
and what the feeling was
at that exact time in that exact place.
Washington's also a city
that's very difficult to shoot in.
You're restricted about
where you can put cameras,
where you can sit,
where you can have a truck,
so it made all the filming there
terribly difficult.
We had a hard time thinking
of what Forrest would say
about the war in Vietnam,
and we really couldn't figure out
what his perfect words would be,
and the idea kind of came in
to have the police stop
whatever his message would be,
'cause we never quite figured out
what words he would use
to describe the war in Vietnam.
By the time he started talking again,
you know it was something brilliant
that he must've said,
even though none of us had heard
what it was.
What also was so wonderful
is how Forrest Gump and Jenny
would meet all over the world together.
Nobody ever questioned it.
They were just so happy
to see them together.
The two days that we filmed there,
the skies were very different.
One day was cloudy
and one was very clear,
and Bob computer-generated
the skies to match.
Every single role was meticulously cast.
Yeah, there were constantly
pictures of references
of what members
of the Panthers looked like,
so we could figure out
where there would be a resemblance.
It was very important
that everybody be realistic
and everybody be authentic. Obviously,
you know, it could not be identical,
but often if you were to take pictures
from who the group really was
and put it up against who were cast,
it would be astounding
how close we came.
Also what was great about Forrest is,
he was rarely violent.
The only time he really ever
would lift a fist was in defence of Jenny.
I think what's difficult
for people at this time
is that they're knowing that Forrest's
character actually has grown,
and Jenny's character is so lost
that she's not really going anywhere
with her life.
Bob had a love of William Castle,
and for me, in particular,
this scene was so much fun
because if you look, Rosemary's Baby
is playing across the street
at the Graumann's Chinese Theatre.
And we actually went
to a friend of mine's,
who happens to be
Bill Castle's daughter,
and we got a copy of the real poster
so we could have
the authentic poster up on top.
We don't quite believe him,
and this wonderful look
that Forrest gives lets us know as well.
One of the other things in the movie
the whole entire time
is that there's this Jenny scene
that goes on,
this wonderful score
that Alan Silvestri wrote,
and it kind of always takes you back
to our feeling
of the love that the two of them had.
And all you need to do
is hear the first couple of those notes
and you know exactly where you are.
The other fun part about the two of them
was you always knew
that at some point,
they'd be back together again soon.
You kind of couldn't wait for it to come.
And so much is always said
with just a look.
What's amazing to look at,
when you look at the movie,
is how many important things
have happened in that span of years.
I mean, our country was at a point
where there were so many changes.
And another funny thing
during this scene was,
when we filmed this scene,
by accident, we had had
the flag of China upside-down
and when we were fixing other things
in terms of doing the special effects,
we put the stars in the right order,
right-side up.
Right at that moment
people knew where you were going,
and they just couldn't wait.
Surprise of this scene,
which is supposed to be New York City,
was shot in downtown Los Angeles.
Gary really did a lot of research
into what a man with no legs,
who was unfortunately a drunk,
a Vietnam vet, would be like,
and I remember him walking through...
Well, we're soon
to get to his apartment,
and wondering what pictures
he would have, and he truly
put himself in the mind and the place
of a man in that situation.
I think often we're reminded
about the pain of the war
and the pain of the times,
without saying anything.
Forrest always had a way
of being on a path to go somewhere
and either bumping into Jenny
or Lieutenant Dan on that way,
and somehow he would get back
on that path.
And in most of the cases,
he was carrying on somebody's destiny.
Even at their most dislikeable moments,
characters like Gary
were still totally endearing,
'cause you know that Forrest
would somehow lead them
in the right way
at some point in the story.
It's only 1972, and I think everybody
who's been with us since the beginning
feels like it's been 30 or 40 years.
And every moment's, kind of, touched
with such bittersweet.
Looking back at this scene,
I think the audience is so emotionally
moved by Lieutenant Dan,
but I think they also were equally
staggered visually by his lack of limbs.
As Forrest left the military,
I think the movie took a different turn,
'cause it was less reflecting
about the sadness and the grieving
of the Vietnam War,
and became about other things.
And once he came home,
he really had to learn his own way,
because he had nobody or no general
or no sergeant or no military
telling him what to do any more.
You notice Bob even had
the little touches of Forrest
whenever he took his picture
with his eyes closed.
We had a wonderful gospel group
that was local,
that we used for all
of these background songs.
The sadness of the movie
for the most part, I think, is lifted
once he gets home and you know
he's following Bubba's wish.
I think at some point Forrest is happy,
'cause I think he thinks
he's with Bubba again.
And I think all of us in the audience
kind of felt that as well.
And for the first time ever,
he's really kind of become a man
with his own journey,
even though it's not so fortuitous
in what his fishing accomplishments
are going to be, as of yet.
To me, this is one of the most
comforting scenes in the whole movie,
'cause you know that moon
is the moon that they share,
and therefore Jenny and Forrest
will be together again soon.
I think people have fun,
because they always knew
that the characters in the movie had
just as much fun with Forrest as we are.
This Randy Newman song
kind of adds to the fun of the moment.
The filmmaking behind this
was extraordinary.
They literally brought in jet engines
to simulate the wind
and blow the rain around
like a real hurricane.
No matter what kind of situation
we got in,
no matter how extraordinary it was,
we had no idea
where it was gonna lead us,
and I think that nobody
during this hurricane knew
that Forrest was going
to come out of it a millionaire.
We had no idea
that Bubba Gump Shrimp
would become the sensation that it did,
that even after the movie came out,
we got demands from Paramount
to mass-produce more hats
that they quickly sold
throughout the country.
And in retrospect,
none of us even would have imagined
that there'd be the demand
for a Bubba Gump Shrimp hat.
I wish we'd known beforehand.
Nora Dunfee was a wonderful actress
who Ellen Lewis found for us
from New York.
She was a very famous acting teacher,
and she just was spectacular.
Once again,
Lieutenant Dan jumping overboard,
I think, is an homage to Eric's theme
of destiny in the movie.
And you're gonna be taken
wherever you're taken.
I think once after Bubba died,
Lieutenant Dan,
when he came back into his life,
did become his best friend.
Little touches throughout the movie
that if you notice now,
there are more mailboxes on this road
than there were before.
So you notice Forrest wore
a blue shirt and khaki pants
through a lot of the movie,
when he was a young boy,
and it was always buttoned up,
until the end of the movie
when you notice
Forrest had grown a little bit
and had unbuttoned his shirt button.
And that was
a conscious choice of Bob's
to show us
how his character had grown.
I think all of us have a gasp in our throat
knowing that this is when
Sally's going to be leaving Forrest,
but we all feel
a little bit more comfortable,
'cause we've seen how he's grown
as a person.
But such a little bit of Sally
goes such a long way,
and you kind of know that
her words will be with him forever.
This was a very funny little moment,
when we came up with the idea
of the fruit company,
because that little icon
let everybody in the world know,
"Oh, my God,
he's taken care of forever."
The little Snapper lawnmower
was a very important thing to Bob,
that he found that exact right model
that he remembered from the early '70s.
It also is important, no matter how much
the rest of the world changed,
Alabama stayed the same.
Every time you went back to that house
and every time you went back
to the room, they always were the same.
So you got a feeling that at least
Alabama was peaceful and tranquil,
even though the rest of the world
was going through so much turmoil.
And we're not sure even if it's real.
For the first time ever, we kind of feel
that Forrest has become a man,
because of his loss
and because of his growth.
And you know Jenny's kind of survived
the turmoil that she's been through,
and we think, finally,
this couple really may have a chance.
This moment you watch Jenny's face,
and you see all the pain
that she's been through,
and, unfortunately,
all the poor decisions that she's made
really come back to her childhood.
I think what Forrest says now
is as poignant as his mother saying,
"Life is like a box of chocolates."
Because it's his view of the world.
I think that we all feel so happy
when Forrest and Jenny are together
because we also know
that he's so happy.
And he so deserves it.
And right now,
we know where we are, 1976.
That ever-famous Forrest pose.
And he probably is
the smartest man living.
Of course, one of the things
that's so wonderful,
so many of the images
that we watch in the movie
are images that we've seen previously,
but we've watched
these characters grow,
and now there's different emotion,
different depth to all of them.
And there she goes again.
I think the movie's about a lot of icons.
You look at the sneakers.
We know the Nike swag.
We can place the time.
And for everybody, they may have
a little bit of different meaning,
but for everybody, they know exactly
what's happening at that moment.
Tom was incredible. Tom worked out
and got into shape for Forrest,
so when he was running,
I mean, he was in amazing shape,
and one needed to be in that amazing
shape, I think, to age those years,
and Tom's known for his discipline
in any role that he portrays,
but I think that this role,
where he really did have to age 20 years
and had to do it mainly with his eyes
and with his facial gestures.
Because, if you notice,
his clothing only changes,
because we begin the movie
and Forrest's top button's buttoned,
and by the time that we end the movie
he's no longer that little boy
whose top button's buttoned,
but he's kind of grown into a man,
and his shirt's a little looser,
and that kind of gives us a little bit
of insight into where he's grown.
But so much of it just came
from looking in his eyes
and understanding
that this character truly did grow,
even with the limited intelligence
that he may have had.
He became a man,
he became responsible,
and he really did, kind of, figure out
what his own destiny was.
Cleverly, they had these splinter teams
that flew all over the country,
and Tom's brother often posed
as his double, just running.
I remember the challenge
was to figure out
how to get the happy face in.
And a little easy move like placing
a muddy T-shirt to his face
created history.
And nobody questioned
what he did right now,
just as they didn't question
what he said with Abbie Hoffman.
And they didn't question when he went
and stayed home
after he had shrimp boats.
And they didn't question anything,
'cause they always, kind of,
felt comfortable that Forrest,
somehow deep inside him,
knew what his own destiny was
and what he was doing for himself.
For me, the fun of it was the irony of,
she ended up living up on Henry Street,
and that happened to be the name
of one of my children,
and it was just a total coincidence
that it was Henry Street,
but in fact,
two blocks from where we were filming,
there really was a Henry Street.
And there he was,
sitting on the bus bench for so far.
Twenty years of stories
and two hours of movie,
and he was just a couple blocks
from where he should have been.
And we also know, for the first time,
that Jenny's found her way,
and we don't quite know why
until we meet their son.
None of us had any idea,
when we met little Haley Joel Osment,
he was going to become
the actor that he is,
and we chose him because we felt
that he was the proper mixture
between a Jenny and a Forrest.
I think that even though
Jenny has told us
that little Forrest
is one of the smartest in his class,
when they move together,
we also know
how smart his father is, too.
Everybody's so happy this moment,
'cause big Forrest
finally has the woman he loves,
a son,
he's at home
and he's joined by his best friends.
And I think they're so happy,
'cause when the man that we met,
everybody thought
was just a common idiot,
and he probably turns out to be
one of the wealthiest men alive,
not in terms of money,
but in terms of what he's obtained
and his goals and his family
and his friends.
You can see,
when Forrest walks in that room,
he's watching the same bed
that he lost his mother in,
and I think he knows deep inside
that Jenny's time is not too long.
I think at this moment,
Forrest has finally explained to us
the significance of the feather,
kind of, destiny,
and floating around on a breeze.
And if you watch,
there'll be the birds for Jenny.
What's amazing, he's probably
become the best father in the world.
What's most amazing to me
when I rewatch the movie
is to watch Forrest go through
so many outrageous journeys
and have so many challenges
and trials and tribulations,
but yet he finds such inner peace
with himself, within his family,
within his home,
and within his friends.
And ultimately,
with Jenny and little Forrest.
When people think about Forrest Gump,
you often think about
all the funny and the hysterical
and the ironic moments
of Forrest put into real-life situations
that we all can remember and visualise,
and I think we often forget, at times,
the poignancy of the movie
and how emotionally moved we are.
When everyone was making this movie,
it was truly a labour of love.
Every single person gave their all,
and none of us had any idea
of the magnitude
of the message that we were about to,
in a collaborative way,
present to the world.
And I think that that's when
movie-making's at its most special,
because when you just do it
for the love of what you're working on
is when magic can happen.